howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus on a single topic
as always links to books articles and
organizations mentioned are available on
the episode page at
jimrodshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
today's guest is brett weinstein
evolutionary theorist
professor in exile co-host along with
heather hang
of the dark horse podcast and last but
certainly not least one of the startup
crew of the game b
movement welcome brett hey jim how are
you doing my friend
i am doing pretty good it's good to have
you back on the show
uh it really is a lot of a lot going on
in the world a lot to talk about
i have noticed yeah it's all you know
you know for the last four years it felt
to me like uh i was in one of those
alternate branches of the metaverse in
the uh
uh one of those forking uh universe
stories right
very weird very oh this forking universe
the multiverse theory in fact actually
my podcast tomorrow we're going to get
pretty deeply into
quantum interpretations and what have
you so i've been reading up on it so if
i nerd out in that direction
that's why that's the reason all right
i'm prepared
all right today we agreed that we're
going to mostly talk about the
unity 2020 effort that you put together
as an alternative to the dem republican
political duopoly
but before we go there let's chat a
little bit about your very recent
banning from facebook i mean what the
what was that all about
what have you learned yeah that's uh it
was fascinating so
your listeners will not for the most
part know anything about my history on
facebook
i was a fairly regular user for
quite a few years and then after
the evergreen meltdown i more or less
had to walk away from facebook because
it became such a toxic
environment so i am a very
occasional user of the platform and in
fact
i don't think i have used it in the last
several weeks
if i logged on it would have been once
and i'm not sure that i posted anything
and in spite of my lack of activity i
was
evicted from the platform which i
discovered when
a friend posted a link in a private
discussion
to something that someone else had
placed on facebook i clicked the link
and a warning popped up that said
that my account had been i've forgotten
the exact language but effectively
deleted that a review had already been
conducted
that i had somehow violated the
community guidelines in no way that was
specified and that the decision
could not be reversed yeah i got it
right here let me read it for you
because i
uh when i saw that when you posted it
over on twitter i said this is a
delectable combination
of both orwellian and kafka-esque
right quite excellent from facebook
you cannot use facebook because your
account or activity on it didn't follow
our community standards which you and i
both know is about 75 pages of
gobbledygook
we've already reviewed this decision and
it cannot
be reversed that's what it said
cannot be reversed has already been
reviewed that's very striking
now my sense is if i was a normal user
of facebook
then i would have engaged in some
activity and i would have been left
scratching my head trying to
wonder where it is that i tripped over
one community guideline or another but
given that i wasn't using the platform
at all it was pretty clear that this was
somehow
either a massive error which is
incompatible with their claim to have
reviewed it
and the decision being irreversible or
that this was personal about something
that facebook didn't like about me and
that it had decided not to wait for me
to do anything it could portray as a
violation of a community guideline and
tossed me off just based on
the uh incompatibility of my character
with their platform or something like
that
of course there's the third possibility
i was i was thinking about this one is
uh you know it could have been an
algorithm run amok uh
but you know the message we have already
reviewed this
decision and it cannot be reversed does
not sound like the thing even the
chuckleheads that
facebook would have given to an
algorithm basically a death sentence
with no appeal
based on an algorithmic checkbox but
with those chuckleheads you never know
uh yes it could also have been uh you
know a conscious decision but there's a
third one also and
maybe this is my occam's razor one i
don't know love know what you think
about it what you've heard
if anything from them and that is a
disgruntled
employee somewhere in the bowels of
facebook who happen to have the power to
do this
didn't like you for one reason or
another and typically about your
political views
and decided to blink you uh so that's
kind of
the third possibility i would put out
there yeah i mean i think
it's going to be somewhere in that
neighborhood but i don't see any reason
to imagine that facebook was not on the
whole
comfortable with the behavior of its
employee
so i should say uh i have
received no communication whatsoever
about what facebook imagines
took place that would have justified
this the only communication i've had
was a reply to my tweet
announcing that i had been evicted from
facebook a tweet that
was uh very widely circulated it ended
up with
i don't know 56 000 likes
so my eviction was noticed by a lot of
people
um including some very prominent ones
and
as the likes and retweets of that
communication mounted a
facebook comms employee named liz
shepard
in the replies said that i
had triggered
a system designed to detect inauthentic
behavior
and that my account had been restored
and they regretted the error which is of
course
inconsistent with what they had
initially said which is that
a review had been conducted and this was
irreversible
now oddly or maybe not so oddly
clicking on the profile of liz shepard
on twitter
reveals that she was formerly with
the democrats and nancy pelosi
so my sense is that somehow
my activities probably my anti-duopoly
activities with
unity 2020 were regarded
as heresy somewhere inside of
facebook and that this action was either
punitive or that they were
booting me because they they didn't want
me saying
inconvenient things um in
some future context like perhaps after
the election
but you still have never you have not
received anything official i just
as far as with respect to official
communications you were found guilty
executed or
condemned to be executed with no appeal
uh then you were released
with no explanation i prefer to think
that i was executed
and that i rose from the dead but um
yeah ah
three days later the groundhog dug its
way out of the ground
it wasn't quite three days but i'll take
it
yeah this is like as i say this is the
perfect uh hell broth of orwell and
kafka
right they don't tell you what's going
on they do what they want
uh for probably uh strategic reasons but
who the hell knows right very very scary
that we have allowed our public square
to be controlled by people like this
uh it's terrifying um because at some
level we don't have an alternative
public square where we can take our
business so we are condemned
to discuss the matters of the day
on these platforms and they have
effectively
infinite discretion with which to decide
who can speak
what to amplify and all sorts of other
things so
i think it is clearly the case
that as we become more deranged
that the uh the ghost and the machine
is these platforms yep it is it is
very very scary particularly those of us
who can think
through uh what the evolution of a
network looks like
when somebody can modulate the
propagation
on the network at their will yes
absolutely it's um it's basically like
the kind of control that a magician
has over what the audience can see
except in this case the audience doesn't
know that they're attending a magic show
exactly the recent film social dilemma
on netflix with our friend tristan
harris
laid out a whole a fair amount of that
but
they didn't quite uh go into this level
of of malice essentially they were more
looking at the implications of uh the
business model right trying to addict
people to dopamine
serotonin response cycles for the
purposes of selling predictive
advertising
which is bad enough but to the degree
that these platforms are
intentionally distorting discourse
particularly
in your case within you know i was one
of those people who came to your age i
think i got about
i don't know 30 000 reads on my various
rants on the topic
uh you know and we were all saying wait
a minute of all people brett
i mean talk about good faith discourse
you may like him not like him agree or
disagree
but he's without a doubt a solid good
faith
discourse kind of guy this is not good
at all yes now there's a question about
whether
um attacking me in this way with
that being my reputation amongst many
people
on frankly all sides of the political
uh discussion whether or not the
spectacular overreach actually in the
end
has made those of us who wish to see
open discussion on these platforms
a bit stronger because uh it has
complicated their story that what
they're really doing
is um eliminating people who are beyond
the pale
yeah i think if indeed this was a
act of malice uh then that is absolutely
true
uh and it's some significant chance that
it was i mean particularly the nature of
that message
we have we have already reviewed this
decision
and it can't be reversed that does not
sound like an automated
uh bot uh you know anyone who would give
that much discretion to a bot that's not
that's not good in its own self
yes now my guess actually would be
uh so you know it was interesting there
was there was one action i could take
on that warning message and it involved
downloading
what facebook called my information
which is to say information that
facebook had collected on me
and uh it was alarming
you know no surprise really but to
actually be faced with what facebook
has accumulated in terms of you know who
i've interacted with
what i've liked uh when i've logged in
all of these things
it's quite clear and you know obvious
that facebook has
more information than the stuff that was
in the pdf file they gave me
but the um the
fact i believe is that facebook a
couldn't possibly have mistaken me
for a bot or anything other than a
person my account was so long-standing
and
behaved so much like an actual human
being that
there's no way you know it would have to
be an amazingly stupid algorithm
that you would never actually empower in
the world to evict people
if it mistook my account but
what they would have known is that my
hesitancy to use facebook in the last
several years
is extreme enough that there's a good
chance
that i wasn't going to log in and
discover that i had been booted
until after the election so i wonder if
they were not
expecting that this would be discovered
at some later date and
that the accident of my having been
directed to a link by a friend
basically brought this into into the
public sphere early
that's interesting and not not
contemplating that they're trying to
disable the
uh the counterwave essentially in
advance preemptively
yes and we know actually uh material
that emerged
yesterday i believe suggests that
facebook
is already building a
mechanism it says for addressing
post-election violence which they
consider likely and i also think
post-election violence is likely but
the question is what exactly is facebook
planning to do
it is planning presumably to control
our discussion with each other in a
situation in which an election
results in a contested outcome and you
know
at some level who the hell are they but
uh
given that they seem to think that they
are entitled to modulate our discussions
with each other on the essential
matters of of our governance i can
imagine that they would view
me as very inconvenient to any narrative
that they want to
portray because i am a
uh a liberal a radical as i've described
myself
and yet i'm not uh in any way
ready to tolerate the influence peddling
of the dnc yeah it's certainly possible
though i will say i mean this thing we
have to be careful about
is uh that
you know it's very tempting to ascribe
behavior to malice when
fairly often it's incompetence and i can
give you a personal example that's to do
with facebook
uh from very occasionally i'll try to uh
do what they call a boost on one of my
podcast episodes i have you know post a
uh
a story about each episode in a very
standard format on
the jim rut show facebook page and a few
other places
uh maybe every few months there's one
that i think has enough profile that
it's worth
throwing 50 bucks on and see what
happens if it works i'll throw another
50.
the most recently the most recent one i
did was with former secretary of defense
william perry
about his establishmentarian a character
as you could possibly get
and his co-author on his new book the
button
a very serious establishmentarian
discussion of nuclear policy
nuclear arms control and control of our
nuclear weapons
and guess what the ad was rejected and i
appealed and they rejected it again
right what the well
so let me ask you a question um i
understand and agree that sometimes
ineptitude creates something that you
would be tempted to dismiss as malice
but it isn't
in that case though i don't know how why
are you sure
that the rejection of that ad
was incompetence when twitter and
facebook and google are you know
not just establishment but they're also
highly partisan
well again william perry secretary of
defense under clinton
uh the basic tenor of the book is
at least partially motivated by distrust
of the psychological stability of trump
if this has any partisan valence which
it does maybe a little
bit it points blue but in a very
establishmentary and blue church kind of
way
so yeah i don't i don't know
uh but anyway and this is not the first
time i had another one uh
jill tarter the uh world's leading
authority on search for extraterrestrial
intelligence
uh her the ad for her episode was also
bounced
and i go what and at that point i was
running a few more ads on facebook and i
had my ad team intervene they got it
turned around and they said
yeah it was a stupid-ass algorithm uh
that somehow decided it was
inappropriate
okay search for extraterrestrial
intelligence and nuclear arms policy
those seem like really bad things to be
talking about
with two of the world's leading experts
on them right i mean
you never know what the algorithms are
worried about it's possible that the
aliens could be underage
[Music]
well actually the other thing is the
aliens could have already infiltrated
facebook and they don't want any talking
about seti um
yep a live possibility anyways well
you know so i think you know let's keep
that in in
a liminal state that yes it could be
malice and i think something about the
wording of that message makes me think
um
okay but uh these guys are chuckleheads
and they up all the time yeah
although
there's something very odd about the
one and only communication indicating
what took place coming from somebody
who is so closely associated with
the dnc yeah that's weird too and also
of course the high hilarity that they
did it on twitter
yes well of course yeah twitter in a
reply
you know reply to twitter and they have
your email right part of signing up for
facebook and you give them your email
uh you know they could have easily
emailed you something uh but yeah
somebody uh
pops into a reply on a stream on twitter
i mean yep
of course uh yeah it is very odd uh
very odd but let's leave it at that we
could talk about the foibles of facebook
and
uh why it's terrible and why frankly
many of us are starting to build
alternatives and
on other platforms and there are many
many uh community
uh type platforms out there where you
can sort of set up your own environment
and many of us are doing that right now
uh and but unfortunately that may have
an even worse effect which is if nothing
at least originally facebook was an open
public square where people from all
sectors
could come together and compare and
contrast their ideas
if if this breakup occurs and those who
are serious about talking about ideas
retreat to our own
private enclaves uh the filter bubble
effect will actually get worse
yep i agree with that and so i think
these people are stupid as
uh for if that's what they're trying to
do and they certainly are i mean they're
bouncing people for point of view
uh all the time you know you know as
much as i think q anon are a bunch of
uh mental defectives uh
people want to you know part if they
want to frankly i don't think it's any
crazier than
the catholicism i was raised right tell
you the truth about equally absurd well
i would say catholicism will a little
bit more absurd uh
and but if you want to champion
catholicism or q anon
in the public square why not
well not only why not i think uh
all thinking americans understand
that whatever you may want to censor the
instinct to do it is
worse than the problem you're trying to
cure yeah
and and we know again every example from
history it never stops with okay oh
nazis bad yes we both agree with nazis
bad
kill nazis with bombs okay
we're there actual german nazis 1933 to
all four killing them so we'll censor
actual nazis you know the few that are
still alive
all right we can agree on that that's
but that's the slippery slope
you know it used to be the liberals yeah
i'm sure you remember the aclu
actually famously fought for the right
of nazis
real american nazis at least to march
through skokie of
a community in illinois that had a large
population of holocaust survivors in it
you know distasteful as
but we used to think that was part of
what america stood for
yep it uh it must be distasteful as the
uh
the majority of the speech we would like
to ban is
there's no good way of being surgical
about it so
we dare not yeah and somebody's uh one
some famous thinker can't remember who
uh of course uh it's easy to defend
speech we agree with you know the
the principles about speech we violently
disagree with
absolutely all right so let's move on to
unity 2020. uh first what was your
motivation and then
you know at the highest level what was
unity 2020
all right um the motivation for unity
2020 which started out under a different
name but
was the recognition that once again
our political apparatus had delivered us
a uh an election in which no
good choices were available every single
person
was going to be forced into engaging
in some kind of harmful
vote or refusal to vote and that this is
a
an unacceptable position to be in and
there's no reason that it should be the
natural state
in a functioning democratic republic and
therefore
we needed to break out of the cycle
that has increasingly caused this to be
the default
well let's let's stop here make clear
this uh specifically
the the choice that was bad was that you
launched it about the time it became
clear that the democratic nominee
was going to be joe biden and the
republican nominee was going to be
donald trump yep that's no choice at all
and so the plan that i announced
was a plan in which we would draft
two individuals they would have to meet
three characteristics they would have to
be
courageous capable and patriotic
and of course would have to meet the
constitutional requirements for holding
the office
we would draft them under an agreement
to
govern jointly by consensus
they would run on a ticket
the top position the presidency would be
established by a coin flip in advance of
uh us draft uh in it after we had
drafted them but in advance
of them arriving on the ballot they
would flip a coin and decide who was
going to run for the presidential slot
uh after four years the positions would
reverse and the person who had
inhabited the role of the presidency
would run for the vice presidency and
vice versa
and this could continue until one person
had inhabited the presidency twice and
was therefore ineligible
for a third term at which point they
would be replaced
by someone suitable i'm not sure if i
said
that these two individuals one would
come from the left and one would come
from the right and the idea was
this would mean everybody would know
that their interests were going to be
represented in the room
where the discussion of what policy
was to be pursued was taking place
so that was the plan and it garnered a
large number of volunteers who were very
enthusiastic
about the plan and a fair amount of
interest
amongst people who recognized that there
was something wrong
with the major party offerings
it did not however garner the
groundswell that would have allowed us
to draft
these candidates we did go through a
nomination process
and we arrived at a ticket the ticket
was tulsi gabbard and dan crenshaw
and what would have
put us in the running was enough of a
groundswell that we could have
drafted those two people um
but that groundswell did not arrive as
much as people were very interested in
unity 2020 that just simply
wasn't enough visible enthusiasm to go
through that process
got it now you told me about it and we
talked about it when you were first
getting ready to launch it and i then
hopped on the internet and
i remember you and i originally got
together
back in the days of the old emancipation
party and this was a precursor to game b
and it's still up our very interesting
reforms and proposals at
emancipationparty.org
and at that time i was the one who was
in charge of learning about ballot
access
and all the things you need to do how to
deal with the federal elections
commission etc
and my take at the time was brett this
is a really
clever idea i love it a lot but there is
no way you're going to get on
the ballot
of very many states starting you know
around april
uh the you know the first deadlines are
coming up in may and the big ones are
coming really soon thereafter
i don't see how you're going to do it so
what was your approach to get it to
getting ballot access
well we uh very quickly looked at the
question of ballot access and you're
right there was going to be no way to go
through the front door and get ourselves
on the ballots of enough states
to to compete in an election
however there was another mechanism
which was the partnering
with third parties that had ballot
access and it could have been
let's say the libertarian party which
has access in all 50 states
it could have been the green party which
had access in
almost all of the states or it could
have been a combination of regional
parties
the problem was this required
a recognition on the part of third
parties
that we were in an emergency situation
in which the particular ideologies that
they represented
were a secondary consideration to
challenging the catastrophe that duopoly
had set us up for
and we did have interesting discussions
back channel with highly placed people
in a number of third parties including
the major ones
however the problem
game theoretically and you know this
could be argued is totally foreseeable
is that in the case where the duopoly
has screwed up
and has delivered a completely
non-viable election
the third parties which ordinarily are
not
competitive see the possibility that
this time might be different
now what we tried to explain
and again back channel this was received
well
was that there was actually some very
good reasons that a third party that was
interested
in long term having its ideological
position advanced
would be interested in partnering with
the unity movement short term
so if sufficient success at the ballot
box
can be attained federal funds go
to the party that has attained that
success in the next
election and so there is potentially a
lot of money for
greens or libertarians or both that wish
to partner
with us what's more the challenge
to the duopoly where it's successful
would have allowed us
to pursue ranked choice voting which
would of course empower third parties
in future elections to advance their
agendas but in the end the
[Music]
public groundswell was too small
and that meant that the third parties
that
held the ballot access that they could
have shared with us
were not interested and i think
understandably so
yep that makes sense so it was an
interesting concept but it had an awful
lot of had to works and
uh you know and the key one was the
groundswell which just didn't happen
yeah now i do in retrospect think that
there is
a better way of conceiving the problem
but i'm not
frankly sure that we didn't have to go
through this exercise in order to figure
out
where we were and uh you know
what was too far outside the overton
window for
the american public to register it even
in a situation
in which it was widely understood that
we were in a no-win situation
you know of course the other one then
this is the the deep problem of the
first past the post systems which we
have in the united states in the uk etc
uh which is from a game theoretical
perspective for
the strategic voter uh it tends to in
under most situations collapse to a
duopoly for good reason
and that is of course the lesser of two
evils phenomenon
uh i you know you see this unity 2020
thing go yeah if everything was perfect
i would definitely rather have tulsi
gabbard and dan crenshaw than
uh the other two alternatives but if i'm
a democrat i'll say i surely don't
want donald trump
and if i'm a republican i'll say i sure
as don't want uh
joe biden so i am not going to take that
risk
that they end up splitting the vote and
uh
uh putting in somebody who i think is
much worse i mean it's the old saying
that the difference between
good and better is a lot less than
between
uh good and worse so the famous
uh lesser of two evils conundrum is i
think a real powerful
game theoretical trap and you have to
somehow get over
a credibility probability threshold
before
the people back away from that attractor
well i i think unfortunately people have
accepted it and they have forgotten to
think about
the logic that actually undergirds it so
in general
the lesser of two evils paradox
may govern the thinking of a strategic
voter
but the first thing to recognize is that
elections are not one-off events they
are
iterated and that changes the game
theory dramatically
so in effect a party that is counting
on well in my case the democratic party
which has long counted on people
to the left of the mainstream the
democratic party to fall in line when it
comes to the election
that that party therefore has no reason
to cater
to the interests of those who have
nowhere to go because of the lesser evil
problem and therefore the way to get
your interest
dealt with is not to fall in line
so from the point of view of multiple
elections taken together
there's a good reason to ignore the
lesser evil paradox
it's also true though that the
republican party
was the uh beneficiary
of the collapse of a previous party
so to the extent that we have a duopoly
with two dysfunctional corrupt parties
and
one is looking for a way out the answer
may involve uh the birth of one or more
new parties that actually give a damn
about our interests
yeah that i agree with for sure but uh
you know
the the space of operating within the
game theoretical constraints of our
constitution make it very difficult
though as you point out it's not
impossible
uh the whigs were the party that were uh
replaced by the republicans and there
was a kind of a fluttery period in there
where there were the free spoilers who
essentially turned into the republicans
uh and there were times in the past
where third parties
uh particularly the progressives in the
late 19th century
and then oddly the socialists uh for a
time in the 20s
got some significant numbers of votes
but didn't come close to that tipping
point
so it's possible but just hard
well it's hard for only one reason
and that has to do with the willingness
of voters to suspend
disbelief in a new direction so
i would argue that there's an awful lot
buried here under the uh
the stone that says lesser of two evils
one thing is that voters
when they engage in voting in a
presidential election are already
engaged in the suspension of disbelief
that is to say the chances that your
vote
will actually alter who takes the office
are vanishingly close to zero and yet
people will spend significant time and
effort to cast that vote
and we re we need them to right the
democracy depends on people suspending
their disbelief
and behaving as if their vote matters
because uh the
the collection of votes does then
reflect the will of the people to some
extent
so the fact that suspension of disbelief
is already a part of voting
means that the possibility exists to
extend it to this
other question and in this case
um one of the things we discovered in
the unity movement was that our movement
was
attractive we structured it by
proposing a draft of one person from the
left and one person from the right
we attempted to steer the middle course
and to draw equally from both sides so
as not to spoil the election
and our internal data of people
volunteering
reflected exactly this there was a tiny
bias in favor of
us appealing to people who would
otherwise have voted for donald trump
but in general it was very evenly split
but what surprised us was that a quarter
of our volunteers were actually drawn
from people who weren't planning to vote
at all and
what this tells us something i've long
been saying is that
those who don't vote really come in two
very different
styles one style is apathetic and
they're just not paying attention
the other style is disaffected these are
people who potentially
could vote but are so fed up with the
process that takes advantage of them
that they don't
and if those people were to tune back
into the process
and vote against the duopoly they are
effectively free agents
their voting for something
hopeful does not actually empower the
greater evil because they weren't voting
in the first place so if those people
were to return
in large numbers then they would be the
most powerful political force in the
country
and the problem is there are many of
these very
standard arguments that cause people to
basically choose what to do in an
election
as a result of a kind of autopilot and
it's it's
unfortunately heading us into
a a an election that
many people regard as in danger of
breaking out into violence
very interesting you point out the
non-voters i funded
a study of non-voters uh
during and after the 2012 uh
election ellen shearer one of the
world's authorities on the non-voter
phenomena and she actually
divided non-voters into five or six
different classes
uh and but roughly you are correct uh
at the highest level you can say there's
a large number of apathetics
but then there are others who are uh
either
uh discouraged by non-alignment from for
a very long time
with the parties or that just don't find
what
what they want on offer from either or
the parties
and the non-voters of even the two more
activists
categories are larger than the
registered members of either of the big
repub
the big parties the republicans or the
democrats absolutely
so any any election cycle that they
wished to announce themselves
as sick of this they could do it
and the hope
with unity 2020 was that it would
catalyze that
the discovery was that people are so
basically they do not reopen the
decision-making process that led them to
their choice in the past
and it's going to take something to wake
them up apparently something
more frightening than a contest between
donald trump and joe biden which i do
find
troubling well of course you know i
think you and you and i
also found when we worked on the
emancipation party that getting people
to
change their political framing is a
really slow work
uh and trying to do it in three months
just isn't going to happen
at least you know that was my take when
i heard the unity 2020 proposal thought
about a little bit did my research i
if i had someone asked me to put money
on it i would have put long odds on it
however if we had more time over you
know you take a
uh at least four year uh time frame and
and don't wimp out like we did with the
emancipation party still regret the fact
i know you
you believe the same thing that we
should have stuck with the party side of
it
in addition to the game b part of it but
we didn't for
for for better and probably for worse
but if one were to start
now right after the election and
attempt to build a political movement
and probably that means a political
party or something very much like a
political party
and attempt to find a way
to mobilize these many tens of millions
of non-voters as well as to pull
people away from the two extremes
there's probably an opportunity there
but it doesn't happen in three months it
doesn't happen in a year it doesn't
happen in two years
even four years might be a push but if
you get it done in
eight years that might be enough yeah if
we're
uh still intact in eight years which is
the reason you know i can
do the logic too and the likelihood of
changing the way american politics works
in three months was
long odds as you say on the other hand
um
as somebody with a fair amount of
experience
in emergency situations
one does very different things in an
emergency
sometimes one does things that under
ordinary circumstances they wouldn't
contemplate and so
unity 2020 was the response
to the perception that some of us have
that this election
is actually a very serious emergency and
that we may not get another shot at this
doesn't mean i think it's more likely
than not that we won't get another shot
but it means the chances of a
catastrophe flowing from frankly the
victory of either trump or biden
is so substantial that uh some of us
felt we had to make an attempt
yeah that wasn't at all opposed to the
attempt but i agree with you uh there is
some chance that this will end badly for
the country i
i'm not i don't believe as direly as
that it's more likely than not or
anything like that but it is worth a
relatively low cost
and as you also pointed out uh much was
learned from this
uh process which we'll talk about in a
little bit uh you know my own view
you know on this is that the there is a
definite availability there uh if one
can gradually build people's confidence
and you know i roughly look at what's
wrong with the world in two ways on one
side we have
maybe 25 percent of the voters who i
call
troglodytes uh you know these are people
who actually
like trump uh not voting for him
essentially cynically because he'll give
them tax breaks or reduce government
regulation
but 25 of people who think trump
actually a good person to be president
of the united states
scares the out of me you know the
light came on for me in the first debate
i don't know why i didn't see it earlier
but trump is a pre-modern person right
he doesn't understand
logic he doesn't understand reason he
doesn't even understand continuity
or thought he would have made a good
kind of germanic tribal leader in 750
a.d you know in the aftermath of the
fall the roman empire or something but
certainly a completely
horrible choice to be a president of a
modern and maybe even now post-modern uh
country
uh who is nothing at all in alignment
with our enlightenment values
on the other half we have the somewhat
smaller but perhaps even more dangerous
15 percent of the population which we
can now call the wokes
who have seemed to have been had their
brains captured by a disease
manufactured on college campuses uh
and this you know this is one of the
strangest phenomena that's happened in
my lifetime in the political sphere that
this
you know self-contained ideological
nonsense
has captured the minds of a lot of
reasonably bright people
and further uh they have essentially
clubbed together and have grabbed many
of the choke points of our civilization
if not by actually real achievement or
distinction
but rather by grabbing those choke
points like the media
corporate hr departments etc and so if
you take 15 works 25
troglodytes that leaves 60 percent of
the voter base that's open for something
i've just sort of tentatively sketched
in this morning i called
the sensible party that's not a bad
place to start
yeah absolutely um now
i will say i don't i think it is just
very difficult to predict what the net
effect is
of either trump being re-elected or joe
biden
being elected in light of what he stands
for
and the necessity to do something
different
you know i've said coalition of the
reasonable uh
you know you have a different
formulation but the fact is
we are going to have to do something
that we are not expected to do we're
going to have
to do something that we are being told
is impossible like
a third party or a movement that
persuades a great many people to return
to the electorate
uh it's unclear what it's going to be
but it has to be something and the fact
that the democratic party is effectively
running the same playbook that it
did so disastrously in 2016
with an even less inspiring candidate
from most people's perspective is
shocking in fact the thing that is most
troubling to me
in this electoral cycle is that people
who see
trump as the only issue until he's out
of
office are not livid
with the democratic party for paving the
way
for him to get there which it did yep
they certainly
did the worst possible job in 2016 as
you and i both agreed and
you know i certainly not only was
supported but i actually campaigned for
bernie in 2016. it was actually working
in the operation but not only not only
did they
run a terrible campaign with a terrible
candidate
but they actually chose trump they
wanted him as the opponent and so they
advanced his candidacy
through surrogates in the press in the
republican field
because he was their uh their desired
opponent yeah they thought anybody could
beat that clown right that's what i
think that was the hillary theory
that was the hillary theory he was the
the pied piper candidate
and so having discovered that these
people are actually
cynical enough to put the country at
risk of a trump presidency
means that we should be banging down the
door of the dnc and saying
how could you do this to us again right
how could you give us in this case
if these people were really believers in
what they tell us that trump
is this tremendous existential threat
which frankly he is
but if they really believed that
themselves then they would have put
their
own corruption and ideology aside and
figured out
what person who was anywhere near the
democratic
slate of beliefs was in the best
position to defeat him in an election
instead they gave us an empty shirt yep
actually i voted for pete boudeg in the
primary uh and not a perfect candidate
in my mind a little too close to the
banks for my taste
but very bright young time for
generational change
uh not captured by the wokes at least he
wasn't then i don't know what's happened
subsequently
a person who could think uh who wasn't
afraid of science
uh not a bad choice but i think
joe was my fifth choice and i ended up
supporting him
against bernie because the 2020 bernie
was not the 2016 bernie
by any means yeah but uh it's
uh you know not great though i will say
you know it's biden is not as talented
and
as or as high equality and intellect as
hillary clinton
but on the other hand he doesn't have
her negatives he's not
ensnarled in her you know networks of
soft corruption
and you know globalist uh elites and
this kind of thing
uh so i think old joe's probably got a
fair good chance to win
well i don't know if he's gonna win i
will say you know what we are
learning about the corruption of the
bidens reflects exactly
my concern which was that the dnc is an
influence peddling
operation that has controlled the party
and that biden was the
the candidate effectively chosen by the
dnc
because he will change nothing and he
will leave their racket
intact and what we are discovering from
the hunter biden laptop
is that this is just literally the case
influence peddling is what they do and
the fact that joe may
seem affable is no reason that he should
inhabit the presidency and
the democratic party should be
absolutely ashamed of having
rallied around him yeah it's it's not a
wonderful choice
however i will also say that the reality
of trump has turned out i believe to be
a lot worse
than the concept of trump a lot of
people i knew
voted for trump in 2016 on the ground so
let's stick a wooden stick in the spokes
of the american show and let's just
tell
show these uh two corrupt parties that
we're gonna uh
vote for this ridiculous outsider who's
gonna shake things up and some of his
rhetoric
actually sounds okay but the reality of
trump as
you know not only a you know truly
psychologically disturbed individual but
also grossly incompetent on the one most
important challenge of his presidency
the
cobot epidemic i suspect uh has changed
the dynamics of the playing field
enough that uh it would seem to me
rather unlikely that he'll slip in again
well
we'll see and the problem is i am now
hearing lots of people
who would never have contemplated a vote
for trump on the basis that
he really is psychologically unfit for
for the office who are voting for him
on the basis that they see no other
structure
that will hold against the the woke
revolution
and i must say as somebody living in
portland where
my city government and state government
have both
failed to hold the line have both
surrendered on the question
of the rule of law i don't know what
happens
if biden is elected right
what if it is if it's biden and he
doesn't bring the federal government
in to reestablish the rule of law what
happens to portland
anybody with any brains gets the
hell out well
so here here's the problem is that what
you have just said
is that there is a rational argument for
somebody
who either lives in portland which is a
small number of us
or gives a about people who live in
portland which presumably is a large
number
right there is a rational argument for
voting for trump
now i wish i didn't have to say this i
didn't vote for trump and i wouldn't
vote for trump i have already voted and
i
did not cast my vote that direction but
i'm not at all comfortable with all of
the people who are saying
actually trump is so terrible you have
an obligation to vote for biden when in
fact
you and i both know that to do so is to
put people living in major american
cities on the west coast
in jeopardy that there is no one who
will stand up for the rule of law
a reasonable point and it does disturb
me and i will admit there were a couple
of
times over the summer where that twin
said god damn it as much i hate that
i
could i suppose imagine voting for trump
but no no
no no no uh common sense uh came in and
you know the guy is psychologically
disturbed uh in a very deep deep level
he's as i said the light finally came
out he's actually a pre-modern person he
does not live in our
in our times actually he's a thuggish
uh tribal leader essentially and he's
pretty good at it
uh and he's incompetent you know he's a
buffoon
on top of it all which is probably the
thing that saved our country
oh there's no there's no difficulty
finding arguments
against a vote for trump the problem is
that the democratic
party did the one thing they needed not
to do
which is to create a scenario so
frightening
that people who would never think to
vote for trump are contemplating it
the works have con have made the problem
more difficult
i mean you know soft corrupt dnc type
democrat
i'll take one of those every day over
trump right we've lived with
soft corrupt democrats since uh you know
at least 1960
when when they get into office uh they
always steal a little bit
uh and uh hey you know that's the price
of
our less than perfect democracy but it
isn't world
threatening bad the wolves have raised
the stakes there's no doubt if it hadn't
been for this woke thing
any democrat uh you know would have won
by 20 points probably
yeah it's it's not just the wokes though
it's the combination
of the vp choice of kamala harris
right which is very frightening in
conjunction
with the wokes and the
hazard that the vp choice may be the
most
important decision that biden makes
because his advancing decrepitude makes
it highly likely
that she will attain the office at least
fairly likely i will say
uh at least a couple of my friends who
were
fi they were lifelong republicans who
were considering holding their nose and
voting for biden the
selection of harris uh turned that off
uh so there's that that's also part of
the consolation there's no doubt about
that
so i just for anybody who's listening
you know i tend to get
uh i'm told by the person manning my
public-facing
email that uh i'm getting lots of irate
email
equally divided between people who think
i'm shilling for trump and people who
think i'm
cryptically suffering from the worst
case of trump derangement syndrome
they've ever seen
and the answer is your mind is making it
hard for you to figure out which side
i'm on
because i'm fed up with this i i dislike
the
the generating function that has put us
in this stupid predicament when there
was no reason we had to be there
we actually had good people running we
had good people running and we could
elect them
but what we have is a system that kills
those things off in the primaries so
that
the american public always loses the
election
usually though not always obama was a
pretty good candidate john mccain for
his flaws
was not a bad candidate uh obama was a
brilliant orator
i really like him as an orator he was a
terrible president
he did a reasonable job of managing the
financial crisis which was the one thing
he had to do
in his uh administration the one thing
trump had to do was manage covet and he
totally failed at it
uh obama was way too cautious for my
mind as
ron paul his chief of staff who got
pissed off and quit
said a crisis is a terrible thing direct
to waste
could he use the financial crisis 2008
as an opportunity to move
america towards a more equal more just
society in a sensible sane way
but he didn't unfortunately he
capitulated to the bankers
i knew the game was over when he
appointed geithner and summers as his uh
secretariat treasurer and his head of
his economic council he was
going to play it safe and go with the
economic status quo
there you go so the data on what he
actually did at a policy level
suggests that he managed the financial
crisis reasonably well
but that was accidental from the point
of view of the american public that what
he was really doing was managing the
financial crisis
well for the real constituents of
the duopoly and it happened that the
american public's interests were well
enough aligned that
that uh you know we had the economy
preserved at some level
but that was the self-interest of the
banks kicking in and
you know the public was not well served
by it which of course
woke a lot of people up to what was
going on caused the occupy movement
uh the tea party movement in the
beginning and and so
in any case i in game b for that matter
right right came from that
we i think we all saw the beast
um clearly for the first time but
uh in any case yeah i do think the
answer is we always lose the election
sometimes we lose it worse sometimes we
lose it better
but the fact that we always lose it
because somebody else has
dibs on power is uh
troubling and it's time we did something
about it all right so let's talk about
that
what can be done you know let's assume
it's the day after the election
and there's a group of us who share your
distaste for the show that we have
year after year after year
and yet we're smart folks we understand
game theory
we understand uh evolution we understand
networked
evolution how can we traverse
these famous traps of difficulty of
launching a third party or at least a
third political movement that acts a lot
like a party
and somehow become credible over the
next four to eight years
well you know i think those of us
who are trying to build something that
captures the imagination
are in an unfortunate learning process
right we are discovering what flies and
what doesn't fly which actually has very
little to do
with what would work if only people
would sign up for it in other words
there's a bottleneck that comes through
what people can imagine and what they
can't
and i think the key recognition
is that a you've got code running in
your mind
that is not there for your well-being
it's there to preserve
something that does not wish to be
displaced and that our survival depends
on us displacing
so finding that malware
is vital and that malware lives in
certain places it lives
in the argument that you must vote for
the lesser evil
it lives in the argument that to vote
for something other than the major party
offerings
is throwing away your vote that a
protest vote is pointless
right these things are wrong the reason
that they're wrong is not obvious
but what you know going into
it is if everybody does what the
autopilot says they must do
if everybody evaluates each decision
locally to that decision we keep ending
up in the same puzzle and
the magnitude of the hazard grows over
time
right that's going to be a disaster
sooner or later if trump
you know scares the hell out of you and
you think my god how could this person
have ended up in such a powerful
position
you ain't seen nothing yet it's going to
get worse that's guaranteed unless we
figure out how to confront the problem
so what that means is something
that you do not expect something that
sounds wrong
is going to have to carry the day now
what is that going to look like
there are a lot of ways we could come at
that problem
but i would say step one is the
recognition
that elections sit in a game theoretic
landscape but it is not a one-off game
it
is always an iterated game and if you
are voting
as almost every american does on the
basis that this
is an isolated election you're probably
doing
yourself and those you care about harm
that the right way to think about
elections is iterated
and therefore at the point that it turns
out that the duopoly robs you of a
reasonable choice
voting against it so that it is so that
it
increases the likelihood that in the
next election you will not be faced with
that predicament
that's the right thing to do but we know
trying to
you know heck you you're a professional
professor of this trying to teach
people uh evolutionary game theory is
not
easy yeah and i you know i don't really
believe that that's the way it's going
to work
um i think there are
what i came to understand in the process
of seeing what happened with unity 2020
and i must say we haven't even gotten to
talking about
what twitter did we will talk about that
before we go
but what i came to realize is that the
problem
was the idea that a groundswell could
arise directly
the way that a groundswell would happen
is
that one has to reach a small
number of highly imaginative
influential people and that they are the
ones who really need to understand
enough game theory or something
very like it in order to be persuaded
that enough is enough and it is the time
to do something
counter-intuitive that
the problem is trying to reach people
directly everybody is embedded
in a network of you know a social
network and i don't mean a platform i
mean an actual group of people
that they care about and those people
all
hold these uh stifling beliefs that one
must vote for the lesser evil or you're
being stupid
um that a protest vote is a waste
and that the thing that is going to
cause that dynamic to break
is people who are smart
who are articulate who are patient who
are
um trusted to stand up and say
you know what we can't keep doing this
and
i think approaching approaching those
people and getting them on board over
time is really the key to the
groundswell that is
going to be necessary one way or the
other it's a it's a start but here
let me throw back at you uh you know
what we've seen over the history
the last several years we've got a
pretty good network now pretty smart
people
right the game b emancipation party your
podcast
rebel wisdom uh there's uh hundreds of
thousands of people now who are
uh i think aware of the issues and are
thinking about them
but there's also actual hard game theory
problems that we as we've talked about
and there's actual real organizing that
has to be done real work
right hard work extremely hard work and
i've known a number of people who've
been involved libertarian party
and you know the number of years they
had to spend until they got the capacity
to get on 50 state ballots year election
after election it took them
many years and it still takes them a few
million dollars every year to make that
happen so
well before you go on let me just say
of course it does the duopoly has set up
rules
to prevent it from being challenged and
one of the things that one has to
recognize is that to the extent
that you think that the game is to win
against goliath by goliath's own rules
you are very likely never to get there
what one has to figure out is how you
escape those rules
and play some game in which goliath is
not the
dominant player or attack at the cracks
at least to start
right and again your knowledge of
evolution you know there's little niches
where new things start
right uh and one i'd like to throw out
for your consideration
is a surprising number of particularly
state legislative
uh races aren't actually contested uh
only one of the major parties actually
runs a candidate
uh and this is what i was about to say
previously with all these
all these a couple hundred thousand
smart people that were
uh network with uh you know being smart
and publishing smart essays on medium
and such and cool videos on rebel wisdom
and things
uh you know aren't enough we've got to
move from ideas to action
and actually getting some people elected
small number
to state legislatures on a
solid honest uh acceptable party for the
american people
might be a way to work that crack to
establish the niche to show that this is
not
craziness that it can be done um i
i see it i'm not sure i actually see the
pathway from
you know uh electing a small number of
people at the state level i just don't
think we have time
to go this route um but i will say one
of the things that i think the unity
movement
did exactly right and that would be
essential
for any effort going forward
is the discovery that the nation
is in need of and ready for
a non-ideological movement and that to
the extent
that many of our fellow travelers fly
under the banner of libertarian or
green or whatever it may be
that they are actually shooting
themselves themselves in the foot
and that what needs to be done is
whatever your ideology is
more important than that is the
elimination of the corruption that has
broken
our electoral system and that
you can be at opposite ends of the
spectrum with somebody and you can team
up on the idea of restoring
the democratic republic to functional
status
because you believe that if the
democratic republic were functioning
that your ideology would win out
and frankly all of us probably ought to
recognize that to the extent that we
have
ideological beliefs some of them are
probably accurate
many of them are probably not and then
what you really want
is for a meritocratic evaluation of what
the best ideas
are and an eclectic slate of
policy proposals and the way we're going
to get there is to get the corruption
out of the way
yeah i'm a little skeptical on again
mobilizing tens of millions of americans
with process
hmm well that's not what i'm saying i
mean for one thing i would say
uh you know you say
having people present on rebel wisdom or
write medium
essays or whatever it is isn't enough
and i fully agree but what you didn't
say is that the answer to the problem
is uh narrative rather than analytical
that the analytics have to be right but
that what really persuades people
is a story that they find compelling and
this is one of the things that those of
us
who are in a position to get the game
theory right very frequently
don't get because we do tend to be quite
analytical and we think that the right
argument should persuade people
and in the end the right argument
effectively
is the foundation of a compelling story
and it is the compelling story that will
allow the movement to be viable i agree
and in fact i quote you
on this actually i thought it was the
most perceptive analysis of the failure
mode of our old emancipation party which
i don't know if you recall saying this
but i do which is we had too many tapas
jeffersons and not enough ben
franklin i do remember saying that
and that stuck with me like you know
kicking the balls right yep that's what
we did
yep yep no uh benjamin franklin uh
you know he definitely captured the
imagination in a particular way and yes
we need uh
we need more of that yeah we need
storytellers interesting yep
well i'm i'm very interested in seeing
what you do i'm a little skeptical on
that a
a new uh party or a new
something like a party can be mostly
process oriented i'm i
do believe we're gonna have to stick
some uh flags in the ground on some of
the big issues of the day
uh but you know they don't have to be in
the conventional fashions
another one that strikes me as i was
just fooling around with the nolan graph
you know the for the the
two axis system it struck me that
there's perhaps an interesting and
curious space that's not being occupied
at all
uh which is an odd hybrid of both
less government and more equality
uh spell that out a little bit yeah you
know for instance
uh you know one of the things that at
least strikes me as
clearly wrong with our society is the
ever-growing inequality at
exponential rates right through the
financial crisis
accelerating through the obama
administration
getting worse uh under trump etc
uh and uh when and you know that drives
the left at some level uh but also you
know it
drove the trump voters at least a lot of
the ones that i've i've talked to
and there has been since 1980
a general distaste for bureaucracy and
government
and more programs as they answered every
problem
and so roughly speaking i
crafted a concept which i call
parametric social democracy
uh you say what the hell is that uh
definitely a jefferson
thomas jefferson kind of thing not a ben
franklin kind of thing and yeah
well turn that over to somebody else
come up with a better name the idea
is to take a relatively small number of
parameters that make a big impact in the
world but don't require
a large government bureaucracy to do
now i'll just run through a quick list
of them fully portable
educational vouchers right uh
don't necessarily need to spend any more
money on education we actually spend
more money on education than most
advanced countries do
and get a lot worse results uh but if we
had
uh all that all that money turned into
personal vouchers for every student
there would be a tremendous ability for
private innovation
uh to create better schools and to fund
homeschooling etc
for those who wanted to use public
schools they could
but they wouldn't be these uh relatively
low efficient
uh politically captured institutions
that we have today
you know for health care medicare for
everybody all the plumbing's there the
hard part
of uh changing medical reimbursement is
the
computer part of it the coding the uh
the processing and actually medicare is
pretty efficient about eight percent of
its benefits
go for admin versus 25 or 30 percent for
the
health care company so a parametric
social democracy
uh means of dealing with health care
medicare for everybody
climate change you know do we need this
vast jobs program
and you know infinite levels of bizarre
regulation that makes it impossible
to do everything uh there's one very
obvious answer
uh to how to start the ball rolling at
least on climate change
and that's a carbon tax that's
relatively hefty maybe 50
a ton today but escalating over the next
20 years to 200
a ton and then stay stationary until we
get to uh
negative carbon but here's the key right
rather than having that be another
source of money for the government it
should be recycled to the
per capita and you think about the
people say wait a minute
wouldn't that mean there's no incentive
wrong every time you make an incentive
a decision to purchase something that's
carbon containing you pay the price
if you spend your money on something
else you don't pay the price
you get the same dividend back from the
recycling of the proceeds per capita
so if you are spending less carbon than
average
you make money off the tax only people
that are spending more carbon per capita
actually pay a net tax and yet every
single decision about carbon
is fully impacted by the uh by the power
of the tax
so obvious to me as the way to go and
yet neither party
has embraced it yeah but why why jim you
know the answer
taxes for the republicans they can't
have the tax words
no it's the corruption the energy
companies
have corrupted both parties no doubt
about that right the energy companies
and the health care companies
and they are the reason that the
uh inequality that you point to is
growing
uh exponentially right this is all
downstream of a system that basically
creates advantage for those who have
political power it's the cycle
um the money on money returns as you say
yeah the classic man and the last one of
course which exemplifies this
is uh a ubi universal basic income which
hey we invented people we called it
citizenship wage in 1987
2013 uh could be funded by the
combination of a vat tax
a wealth tax and the elimination of the
other welfare systems
uh but of course huge vested interests
opposed to it
but if we had a party that was not
captured and i don't think we'd build a
party that was captured would we now
brett
no no certainly not and that was we
would say from day one we are here for
the american people
and we can get more equality and less
government
by powerful parametric changes in how we
operate our system
and because we're not corrupt we're
going to push these things even though
it
gores the bowl of some rich and powerful
vested interest
yeah now the question is do you need to
divorce
these particular policy objectives
from a force that unites us all
to oust the duopoly or could you
conceivably do what i think you're
suggesting
which is that you make those one effort
my guess is if you make them one effort
you'll lose
yeah there is a problem which is that
our current tribal alignments will
continue to attract people
uh because of disagreements with some of
the things in the package
yep however uh i'm not sure i think we'd
have to
focus group it polling do it et cetera i
have
more confidence in that frankly though
than a you know pure process
approach oh we're gonna we're gonna be
for good government uh
rank choice or range choice voting maybe
liquid democracy
uh and some improvements in how uh
congress is administrated i can see
people's eyeballs rolling back uh pretty
quickly if we try to pedal that as the
as the core of the opportunity well i
see i see there is another
possibility i would argue that
we actually have discovered
the best possible state
for our system we've spelled it out
we've never come
close to attaining it but we know what
it contains
and what we are fiercely divided over to
the extent that our disagreements are
not about corruption but they are about
honest uh different perspectives
what we're actually divided over is how
close we are to the objective
what remedies would be worth their
cost and hazard to get us closer to the
objective
and that in effect if we spelled out
the things that we actually agree on you
know
decent people all agree that
opportunity ought to be broadly
distributed and that
there ought to be no bias in the market
that
favors one group over another right
so if we spelled out the meta level of
what the
the goal that you ought to unite all
americans is
and we spelled out that the primary
obstacle to it
was the corruption of our system but we
left
the ideological aspects aside
so that people could um battle that out
later when the system
was free uh free of corruption enough
that those discussions could be had in
an honest context
that we might have the best of both
worlds that's interesting i like
i think i like that we'd have to see if
one could craft a list of such
values that was rich enough to not be
banal
and uh yet at the same time wasn't
overly determining
and tilting the party to the to the red
or the blue
uh my thought is that actually and i
must say i've
lived now for a number of years as
neither fish nor
foul um you know i'm a liberal
but i'm embraced more frequently over on
the conservative side
so i've spent a lot of time talking to
people and my sense is that actually
that picture of what decent americans
really want
is readily paintable and it resonates
very very well
and that people actually are relieved to
discover
that they don't really differ over the
things they thought they might have
differed over because
when it comes down to it the only people
who oppose these things
are those who are
rent seeking on the basis that they
don't exist
that's uh a very interesting idea i
think that's uh
that's worth pursuing i can see that it
avoids
a trap that comes from being specific on
the policy details
yep and it might just be strong enough
to get the ball rolling
yep particularly if there's a strong
emphasis on process
as well because people say all right how
are we going to get to this promised
land this promised land sounds pretty
good
why is corruption keeping us from
getting to the promised land and what
are you talking about with respect for
process reforms
uh to get us there then it gives a
motivation for the process reforms yep
exactly i like this this is good this is
good
all right let's turn to the final topic
uh before we wrap up and i should bring
a surprise on you
uh which is uh let's do talk a little
bit about
this uh really uh disturbing uh
event where uh just as unity 2020
started to get some real
uh attention uh twitter
decided to ban your hashtag even ban
links to your site tell us what happened
there and about when
so uh it was the final night of the
republican national convention
as donald trump was uh was collecting
his nomination
we attempted to to um
boost a hashtag just say no to donald
and joe
and we did this we discussed you know
that we would do it and also you know
the entire unity movement is composed of
volunteers
and people uh advanced that hashtag on
twitter
and what happened was actually it did
trend
during the final night of the the uh the
republican convention
and the next thing we knew our account
the uh the only official account of
the movement at articles of unity
was suspended again no explanation
back channel discussion actually with
jack of twitter revealed
that we were accused of having
registered a large number i believe he
said 50 accounts
for the express purpose of amplifying
the hashtag
falsely now this shocked us because we
had not registered any accounts
for that purpose people were using their
own accounts for it we were using our
official account
for it um what we discovered in
a an extensive internal investigation
that we conducted was that there was no
truth whatsoever to
what twitter was saying what there was
were a large number i say a large number
maybe it's
a dozen or slightly more than that
dedicated accounts that were opposed
to the unity movement who reported us
claiming that we were violating terms of
service which we weren't
the shocking thing though is that not
only did twitter suspend us
and accuse us privately and unofficially
of behavior that we didn't engage in but
the account remains suspended to this
day
there has been no opportunity to appeal
there has been no official explanation
there has been no ability
to look at whatever evidence twitter
thinks it has
the the link is just uh the account is
just simply
dead what's more
during this episode twitter
created some kind of algorithm that
spotted posting of a link to our website
and prevented the tweet from going in
other words the
link declared the website dangerous
or in some danger of doing harm and
prevented a person
from tweeting those links jack
privately admitted that this was uh
unacceptable and that was reversed
but to this day if you attempt to link
to our website
in a twitter dm you as the person
dming the link will see it as normal the
person that you send the link to
will see a warning instead that will
hide the website and declare it
suspicious
and possibly harmful so twitter has
pulled out the big guns
to oppose the unity movement on the
basis
it seems of false accusations from
people who
dislike the unity movement and with no
evidence of wrongdoing
we know that there was none because we
went through the effort of
doing a thorough investigation but you
know as one discovers with these
platforms
once they decide you're guilty of
something there's just simply
no opportunity for redress yeah this
strike to me is
a considerably more disturbing
pattern than the uh than you getting
booted off facebook and then brought
back
quickly uh i mean this is even more
deeply orwellian and kafka-esque
yeah it's i mean it's it's quite clear
what it is and the very fact that the
uh movement that they opposed is one
that is challenging the duopoly it's
obviously motivated by proper
patriotic democratic values the audacity
to challenge such a movement even if you
think it's wrong-headed
right this is the united states we
are allowed to to challenge
perceived corruption in our governmental
structure this
in fact it's our patriotic duty to see
to do it if we see it
and to have twitter decide that we don't
have the right to do that on their
platform is really
jaw-dropping yep and for uh people out
there go to articlesofunity.org
and you can see what horrible thing this
is that got banned
uh it's there's too much thomas
jefferson not enough ben
franklin uh but it's certainly not very
inflammatory at
all uh your ninth grade civics teacher
would have approved yeah
uh so what the right
exactly it's uh very disturbing
and you know combine this with the
facebook episode and you know
and it was interesting when we were the
game beat crew were out there
campaigning for your
uh for the reversal of this
decision uh we turned up dozens of
people that this had
happened to on facebook where they were
just banned uh given
you know some oracular reason read our
72 pages worth of uh
rules and you can figure it out and told
they had no right to appeal
uh and unfortunately they didn't have uh
you know a large mob that could be
stirred up on their behalf
and they were just yep i i agree
many of them contacted me and said this
and i'm
not really in a position i don't even
know what to do with it because i of
course can't evaluate whether they were
tossed off for some reason or not
but yes this appears to have happened to
a large number of people
i'm in the lucky position of being able
to
create enough noise and my friends
create enough noise to get it reversed
but
it's very clearly a hazard to to regular
folks and we ought to be
quite alarmed at it seems like this is
an excellent process uh proposal for
what comes next politically right uh you
know
to essentially find some means by which
due process
and transparency must be given in these
things
yeah i mean one of two things has to be
true either there has to be a public
on-ramp
to the internet so that we can have
platforms in which this is not
uh a possibility because we do have free
speech protections or
protections that are up to date for the
21st century have to be generated and
they have to apply to these platforms
because at the moment
we have the founders worst nightmare
of a situation in which we cannot openly
discuss
the political situation of the day
and it's unfolding because we are now in
a position of discussing these things
in a technological venue that the
founders couldn't possibly foresee
and yet clearly fits the role of the
public square
it's the public square it's the public
square you know to the 10th power
but you know we have to address this one
way or the other there has to be a
public square in which our rights to
discuss
things are guaranteed i'd suggest that
would be
uh one of the core things that ought to
be on this new political movement saying
here's our
uh here's what needs to be fixed and
whether we go and actually say how that
would be another
question uh but uh at a minimum should
lay out the problem
very clearly because unfortunately as
you know we're trying to do with the
unity 2020 movement
this is an issue that affects both the
right and the left right uh
these guys go after all kinds of people
they don't like uh you know
if this faction on the left they don't
like they go after them you know people
on the right they go after them people
in the middle like you they go after
them so this is
uh well probably there's a political
bias in it i would suspect there is at
least
uh in reality they're also hammering all
kinds of people
uh some of it more or less randomly or
anybody
i guess it's not really random because
anyone who challenges the stan
status quo these are become a force for
the status quo
which is remarkably annoying since these
were uh you know revolutionary upstarts
not that long ago
in silicon valley that were trying to
change the world 100
agree but now they've been captured by
making the big mistake i go in public
and you know going to
davos and places i was invited davos
once i told them go themselves
right
uh i'm going to go hang out they're
right but
you know these guys do they go to davos
and they have sold out
so whether it's via building a
competitor which is unfortunately from a
network effects perspective
difficult but again not impossible
probably easier than starting a third
party
or via government regulation we must
have an
honest public square there can be little
doubt about that in my mind
yep i couldn't agree more all righty
well we're coming up on our
90 minute time here and i'm gonna tell
you a little surprise that i
created for you which is last week
actually right
as you got banned by facebook i went on
godaddy and registered
brettweinstein2024.org
[Laughter]
well uh let's hope we live that long
and uh whenever you want it let me know
and i'll transfer it to you
all right well thanks so much jim that's
really that's really awesome
yeah you're not trying to get me killed
are you
the hell now if anybody kills brett i
will track you down and kill you you
anyone who listens to my show knows that
i'm capable of doing it now we're
talking
yeah so thanks brett for a great
conversation hey let's get to work right
after november 3rd this is
really important stuff let's do it i'll
bring a shovel
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com